# Niles Rowland • 5050 SE 40th Ave. Apt 3 • Dania Beach, FL 33314

954-588-6693 • niles.d.rowland@gmail.com • http://think-knot.com

## **Summary of Qualifications**

Expert qualifications in system administration, web application design, e-commerce, and search engine optimization with an extensive background in the following broad-based competencies:

**System Administration Programming Database Design/Administration** Web Site Design **Internet Marketing E-Commerce** 

- Proven ability to discover and implement software solutions for a wide variety business applications
- Demonstrated talent to apply existing knowledge base for problem solution
- Recognized capability to quickly learn and adapt new technologies

# Commonly used technologies and techniques:

LAMP	PHP	OOP	MySQL	Agile Practices	<b>Unit Testing</b>	Scrum
CakePHP	Zend	CodeIgniter	Drupal	Joomla	Mambo	Smarty
Javascript	jQuery	Ajax	CSS	HTML	<b>Test Driven Development</b>	
Git	Subversion	Apache	Nginx	MVC	Laravel	Jira
Vagrant	Composer	Bootstran	NodeJS	NPM	AWS	

## **Professional Experience**

# Senior PHP Developer

Taylor and Francis Group

Boca Raton, FL

2014 - 2016

- Maintain and update high traffic web application written using PHP/Bootstrap/Javascript front-end based on the CodeIgniter framework.
- Maintain and update high traffic web application written using PHP/Bootstrap/Javascript front-end based on the Laravel framework.
- Create/maintain/update composer packages allowing the CodeIgniter application front-end to make the SOAP calls necessary to query the common core Java API.
- Create/maintain/update composer packages allowing the Laravel application front-end to make the SOAP calls necessary to query the common core Java API
- All work was done in a team environment with the code bases being maintained in Git and Subversion repositories using JIRA to track tasks.

# Senior PHP Developer

Real Local Pages, LLC.

Plantation, FL

2012 - 2013

- Maintain and update Business-to-Business application written in PHP and Javascript built on the CakePHP 1.3 and jQuery frameworks using MySQL database for data storage. This application and database served multiple B2B websites.
- Creation and implementation of user interfaces for numerous websites from mockups.
- Developed and implemented strategy to migrate the above application and database to new hosting service without service interruption.
- Developed automated systems to reduce the number of personnel required to maintain the application.
- Developed and implemented initial organization-wide strategy for software version control using git.
- Design and develop Web 2.0 B2B social media application built on CakePHP 2.4 and Jquery.
- Maintain and administer dual machine RHEL system consisting of MySQL database server and Nginx web server

# Senior CakePHP Developer

2010 - 2011

#### Zumba Fitness, LLC.

Hollywood, FL

- Develop software with the CakePHP framework using best programming practices as applied to the latest MVC paradigm and PHP Object Oriented Programming.
- All work was done in a team environment with the code bases being maintained in Git and Subversion repositories using JIRA to track tasks.
- Accomplishments include:
  - Creation of a CakePHP plugin to facilitate Role Based Access Control (RBAC)
  - Creation of a CakePHP plugin to allow for the creation and redemption of coupons to be applied on any of the site shopping carts or stores. Coupons could be restricted to a certain store, product, or role. Coupons could be a set amount discounted, a percentage of the total discounted, or free shipping.
  - Creation of a CakePHP helper to apply dynamic validation rules depending on the location of the user.

#### **Senior Software Architect**

Cake Development Corporation

Las Vegas, NV

- Develop software in the CakePHP framework using best programming practices as applied to the latest MVC paradigm and PHP Object Oriented Programming
- All work was performed remotely with team members maintaining close and immediate contact via IRC and Skype allowing members to be physically located across 4 continents.
- The code bases were maintained both in Subversion and Git repositories with tracking systems to list bugs, enhancements, etc. that required work.
- Accomplishments include:
  - Creation of a CakePHP plugin for OpenId according to the OpenId 1.1 specifications allowing for both consumer and identity provider. The specifications make extensive use of the Diffie-Hellman key exchange cryptographic protocol. The plugin is licensed under the MIT license.
  - Extensive work creating reusable code for social networking applications

# Program Design and Development/System Administration/Internet Marketing The Neters Group Fort Lauderdale, FL 2001 – 2008

- Design/develop interactive commercial websites used to promote and sell products and services using Linux/ Apache/MySQL/Perl/PHP (LAMP) technology. Many of the sites were built on MVC frameworks utilizing AJAX techniques.
- Conceived/designed and developed a system of powerful web-based applications used to administer/maintain and
  create HTML formatted emails along with the associated web site using PHP/Perl/MySQL/HTML/Photoshop.
  The site's purpose was to attract members to a double opt-in mailing list which was then used for targeted email
  marketing. This system also included the data storage and retrieval mechanisms required to analyze the effectiveness of the marketing.
- Optimize websites for search engine effectiveness.
- Installation/configuration of Linux/Windows operating systems; installation/configuration web servers; installation/configuration of SQL servers.
- Designed and created quality control procedures for activating new clients exchanging information between various data sources via XML/WDDX.
- Created system documentation using SGML converting it to various output formats using JADE
- Provided administration and consultation for various SOHO networks and systems.
- Responsible for content, implementation, and design of various web sites used to increase company web visibility.
- Developed strategies and promotions designed to increase web traffic from various sources including search engines, printed materials, and bulk emails
- Designed/installed/configured bulk email system capable of sending over 3 million emails/day.
- Installed and configured Linux Fedora and SSL/PHP capable Apache web server on numerous machines

#### **Educational Background**

**Associate in Arts** (Emphasis on Electronics and Computer Science)

1987

Olympic College, Bremerton, WA

Computer Science Studies

1989 - 1993

2008 - 2010

University of California at Riverside

#### Major Areas of study:

- Mathematics through multi variable calculus
- Structured programming using Pascal, C, and C++
- Theory of algorithms and data structures
- 80x86 assembly language programming
- Computer modeling and simulation
- Theory of automata and computer design

### Military Experience

**United States Navv** 

1977-1987

(EM1/E-6 Nuclear Qualified)

- Division Leading Petty Officer in charge of all shipboard electrical maintenance and repair
- Responsibilities included electric plant watch-stander training and qualification
- Accepted honorable discharge in October 1987 to pursue other career options